Thomas D. White Papers
Thomas D. White Papers
1945-1961
White, Thomas D. (Thomas Dresser), 1901-1965.
5.5 linear ft.
Papers of the U.S. Air Force officer and Air Force Chief of Staff, 1957-1961.Collection contains communications (1948-1961), including correspondence and memoranda; memorabilia (1945-1954); and personal office files (1953-1961). Correspondents include Hanson Baldwin, Omar Bradley, William C. Bullitt, Arleigh Burke, Richard E. Byrd, Dwight D. Eisenhower, W. Barton Leach, Curtis LeMay, Lyman L. Lemnitzer, George S. Myers, Thomas S. Power, L. Mendel Rivers, A. Willis Robertson, Carl Spaatz, Stuart Symington, Maxwell D. Taylor, Lowell Thomas, Nathan F. Twining, Lee Wulff, and others.
148752
Biographical History
Thomas D. White (1901-1965) was an American Air Force officer and Air Force Chief of Staff, 1957-1961. He retired from the military in 1961 with the rank of General.
Born at Walker, Minnesota, August 6, 190, he graduated from St. John's Military Academy, Delafield, Wisconsin, and received an appointment to the U.S. Military Academy at West Point. After graduation from the Academy in 1920, he entered the Infantry School at Fort Benning, Georgia, and in July, 1921, went to the Panama Canal Zone for duty with the 14th Infantry.
Returning to the United States in September, 1924, he entered the Air Service Primary Flying School at Brooks Field, Texas. Upon completion of the course, he transferred to the Air Service Advanced Flying School at Kelly Field, Texas, from which he was graduated in September, 1925. He then joined the 99th Observation Squadron at Bolling Field, Washington, D.C.
In March, 1927, he transferred from the Infantry to the Air Corps and was assigned to the Military Attaches' office in Peking, China. He returned to his duties at Bolling in March, 1931, and was assigned to Moscow, Russia, as Assistant Military Attache. A year later, he became Assistant Military Attache to Italy and Greece.
White returned to the United States in May, 1937, to enter the Air Corps Tactical School at Maxwell Field, Alabama, and upon graduation in September, 1938, entered the Command and General Staff School at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas. Following completion of the course in June, 1939 he was assigned to the office of the Chief of Air Corps in Washington.
In April, 1940, he became Military Attache at Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, and the following August was named Chief of the U.S. Military Air Mission to Brazil. It was during this time that General White developed his interest in ichthyological research.
Returning to the United States in March, 1942, he became Assistant Chief of Staff for Operations of the Third Air Force and subsequently was appointed Chief of Staff. In January, 1944, he was named Assistant Chief of Air Staff for Intelligence at American Air Force headquarters in Washington.
In September, 1944, White was assigned to the South Pacific as Deputy Commander of the 13th Air Force. In this capacity he served in the New Guinea and Southern Philippines campaigns, and participated in the assaults in Palawan, Zamboanga, in the Philippines, and Tarakan, Borneo. During the latter operation he was temporarily in command of the 13th Air Force.
In June 1945, as commanding general of the Seventh Air Force, General White established it as a component of General George C. Kenney's Far East Air Forces. The Seventh, then on Okinawa, engaged in the air assault on Japan and was charged, in addition, with the air defense of the Ryukyus. General White was transferred with the Seventh Air Force to the Hawaiian Islands, in January, 1946, and the following October was appointed Chief of Staff of the Pacific Air Command in Tokyo, Japan, which was redesignated the Far East Air Forces in January, 1947.
In January, 1948, White became Commanding General of the Fifth Air Force in Japan, and the following October he returned to the United States to become director of Legislation and Liaison in the Office of the Secretary of the Air Force. General White contributed greatly to the Air Force programs by defending before Congress the position of the Air Force during this period. His success on this assignment was due in a great measure to the various diplomatic and political friendships gained throughout his numerous tours of duty abroad and in Washington.
In May, 1950, White was appointed Air Force member of the Joint Strategic Survey Committee in the Office of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. In November, he became Special Assistant to the Deputy Chief of Staff, Operations, Air Force Headquarters. The following February he was appointed Director of Plans Office of the Deputy Chief of Staff for Operations. In July, 1951, General White was appointed Deputy Chief of Staff for Operations.
General White received his four-star commission in 1953, and was assigned to duty as Vice Chief of Staff, USAF, Pentagon. He continued in this assignment until 1957, at which time he was appointed Chief of Staff, USAF, by President Eisenhower.
In 1961, General White retired from the Air Force, but he continued as a military analyst and became a member of the boards of directors for various corporations, such as Eastern Air Lines, and Aeronca Manufacturing Corporation. He was also a member of the General Advisory Committee of the U.S. Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, and a contributing editor of Newsweek magazine.
General White was married to the former Constance Rowe. He died in December, 1965.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Thomas D. White Papers consist of communications, memorabilia, and personal office files.
Communications, 1948 to 1961, consists of correspondence and memoranda. In general, correspondence deals with semi-official military topics, such as Air Force appropriations, budget difficulties, establishment of the Air Force Academy, and congratulatory messages concerning promotions. A substantive portion of correspondence, however, deals with ichthyological research and recreational fishing, two of General White's main interests. Correspondence also includes original indexes, prepared by General White's staff, of incoming and outgoing letters arranged chronologically. Although the indexes are incomplete, they provide abstracts of the subject matter of each indexed letter. A brief list of notable correspondents and the inclusive dates of their correspondence is included at the end of this description. A selective card file index of additional correspondence may he found in the "Finding Aids" file under General White's name. Memoranda includes interdepartmental communications, mainly dealing with questions of protocol and temporary duty, assignments.
Memorabilia dates from 1945 to 1954, and includes biographical and miscellaneous printed materials.
Personal office files consist of official forms, public statements, and miscellaneous material dating from 1953 to 1961. Public statements include transcripts of General White's oral explanations of Air Force policy and its relationship to other branches of the armed forces. This section also contains clarification and corrections of the statements by the Departments of Defense and State prior to their release to news agencies. The miscellaneous category consists of various types of material dealing with travel and information on fishing campsites.
Noteworthy correspondents and the inclusive dates of their communications are as follows:
Baldwin, Hanson W. 1951-1956
Bradley, General Omar N. 1949-1953
Bullitt, William C. 1953-1959
Burke, Arleigh 1957-1959
Byrd, Richard E. 1952-1957
Caniff, Milton 1955
Cooper, Merian C. 1953-1954
Drummond, Roscoe 1957
Dulles, John Foster 1955
Eisenhower, Dwight D. 1952-1960
Evans, J.K. (American Legion) 1953-1960
Gardner, Arthur 1955-1956
Johnson, "Lady Bird" (Mrs. Lyndon B.) 1955
Kefauver, Estes 1950
Leach, W. Barton 1957-1960
LeMay, General Curtis E. 1951
Lemnitzer, Lyman 1953-1959
MacArthur, General Douglas 1953
McKnew, Thomas W. (National Geographic Society) 1956-196
Myers, George S. (Stanford University) 1956-1959
Power, Thomas S. 1951-1953
Rivers, L. Kendal 1954-1959
Robertson, A. Willis 1957-1958
Spaatz, Carl 1957
Storey, Margaret (Stanford University) 1956-1959
Symington, W. Stuart 1949-1957
Talbott, Harold E. 1957
Taylor, General Maxwell D. 1953-1958
Thomas, Lowell 1957
Thurmond, Strom 1957
Twining, General Nathan F. 1954-1960
Vandenberg, Hoyt S. 1951-1953
Westmoreland, General William C. 1960
Whitehead, Ennis C. 1951-1958
Wilson, C.E. 1956-1957
Wulff, Lee 1952-1959
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and memoranda are arranged chronologically. Remaining material is arranged alphabetically, except for the subset of public statements which are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has a number of collections relating to military personnel and military history. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Baldwin, Hanson Weightman, 1903-1991.; Bradley, Omar Nelson, 1893-1981.; Bullitt, William C. (William Christian), 1891-1967.; Burke, Arleigh A., 1901-1996.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Leach, W. Barton (Walter Barton), 1900-1971.; LeMay, Curtis E.; Lemnitzer, Lyman L. (Lyman Louis), 1899-1988.; Myers, George S. (George Sprague), 1905-1985.; Power, Thomas S. (Thomas Sarsfield), 1905-1970.; Rivers, L. Mendel (Lucius Mendel), 1905-1970.; Robertson, A. Willis (Absalom Willis), 1887-1971.; Spaatz, Carl, 1891-1974.; Symington, Stuart, 1901-1988.; Taylor, Maxwell D. (Maxwell Davenport), 1901-1987.; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981.; Twining, Nathan F. (Nathan Farragut), 1897-1982.; White, Thomas D. (Thomas Dresser), 1901-1965.; Wulff, Lee.; United States. -- Air Force.; United States. -- Air Force, Officers.; Aeronautics, Military -- United States.; United States -- History, Military -- 20th century.; United States -- Military policy.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Memorandums.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Aeronautics.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Communications
  - Correspondence
    - Index, covering Jun 26, 1953 to Dec 29, 1960, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1948-1952, 14 folders (Box 1)
    - 1953 Jan-Nov, 15 folders (Box 2)
    - 1953 Dec-1954 Dec, 19 folders (Box 3)
    - 1955 Jan-Sep, 15 folders (Box 4)
    - 1955 Oct-1956 Dec, 19 folders (Box 5)
    - 1957 Jan-Aug, 18 folders (Box 6)
    - 1957 Sep-1958 Aug, 21 folders (Box 7)
    - 1958 Sep-1959 Aug, 18 folders (Box 8)
    - 1959 Sep-1960 Dec, 22 folders (Box 9)
  - Memoranda
    - 1950 Jul-Dec (Box 10)
    - 1951 Jan-Jul (Box 10)
    - 1953 Jan-Dec (Box 10)
    - 1954 May-Oct (Box 10)
    - 1955 Jan-Dec, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1956 Jan-Dec (Box 10)
    - 1957 Jan-Dec, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1958 Jan-Dec (Box 10)
    - 1959 Jan-Nov, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1960 Feb-1961 Jan (Box 10)
- Memorabilia
  - Biographical Material, undated; typescript, reproduction, typescript copy (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1945-1951; undated (Box 10)
  - Clippings, USAF; news release, printed material, 1952-1954; undated (Box 10)
- Personal office files
  - Official forms, 1955; 1959 (Box 10)
  - Public statements, printed material
    - 1957 Jul-1959 Jun, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1959 Jul-1961 Jun, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Corrections by Dept. of Defense and Dept. of State, 1957 Nov-1959 May; 1959 Aug-1961 Apr; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Calvin Bullock Forum, Harvard Defense Policy Seminars, printed material, 1958-1961 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Fishing, undated (Box 11)
    - Photographs (Box 11)
    - Travel vouchers, 1953-1959; undated; 2 folders (Box 11)